Comp 2071: Data Structures 
 
Spring, 2016 
 
Supplemental information for Lab 5: Hash Tables 
 
This supplement should clarify the construction and analysis of your HashTable implementations.  Questions?  Ask! 
 
HashTable size 
The initial assignment/write-up requires you to prompt the user for the initial size of the hash table.  You have two choices for handling the supplied value: (1) use it as is even if it’s not prime or (2) accept any value and increase it to the next (larger) prime number if it isn’t already prime.  Regardless of the initial size of the table, all resized tables must have a size which is a prime number. 
 
You may optionally provide a constructor and/or mutator to control the resize behavior with respect to whether the size of the table must be prime.  By default, ensure that the table size is prime but you may add an attribute which will prevent resizing to a prime and simply use twice the size of the existing table (or the specified initial size).  If you include this option, you must provide a mechanism for the user to turn it on/off. 
 
 
Sample runs 
I provided sample text files for you to process.  Your code must not include any path specification to them.  Put the files in the default folder (typically the project root folder).  I must be able to run your program on my computer without modification - I know your folder organization doesn’t match mine. 
 
For each file, run your solution several times with different initial table sizes.  I suggest that the sizes include a small initial size (e.g. 7 or 11), a large size (e.g. larger than the number of words in the file), and an intermediate value (e.g. approximately 10-20% of the number of words in the file).  You are welcome to try other values too. 
 
You may set up your driver program to automatically process each of the files (preferred) rather than having the user select or specify which file(s) to process. 
 
The provided files include punctuation and varying case.  You could simply take each token from a file and add it to the dictionary/hash table unaltered.  However, it is more interesting/useful to minimally make the processing case-insensitive (“The” and “the” should be considered the same).  Beyond that, I leave it to you to handle punctuation – most likely to remove it – especially trailing periods, commas, etc.  I leave it to you to decide how, if at all, you handle possessives (e.g. “boy’s”).  What do you do with non-words: numbers, dates, email addresses, URLs, etc?  Include a brief statement in your write-up what you did to clean up the text before giving it to the hash table.  For this assignment, it is not appropriate for the HashTable class to change the key – only WordCount may do so. 
 
 
Load factor λ 
The load factor is calculated as: 
 
 λ = # of entries in the dictionary / # of locations in the hash table 
 
where the # of entries in the dictionary is the number of distinct words you added to the table and the # of locations in the hash table is the size of the array, not the number of buckets in use. 
 
I shouldn’t need to tell you this, but make sure you are calculating and manipulating the load factor properly: it is a real number - treat it accordingly! 
 
For separate chaining (buckets), the recommended (default) threshold for λ should be 1.0.  If λ reaches or exceeds 1.0, you must resize the table. 
 
You may optionally provide a constructor and/or mutator to control the resize behavior with respect to the load factor threshold (default to 1.0 but allow the user/caller to provide a different value) to determine when to resize the table. 
 
 
Table metrics 
You must be able to display a set of metrics about the hash table.  This can be implemented as a public method in the HashTable class.  You can either have this method display the metrics to the console, a file or GUI, or it can return the metrics as a String (or other object) which the caller can display.  Optionally, you may create a utility class to collect and calculate the metrics.  Note that some of the metrics processing will probably exist in the LinkedList class. 
 
The metrics must include: 
• current table size 

• number of entries in the dictionary 

• load factor λ 

• number and percentage of buckets in use 

• minimum, maximum, and average (mean, median, and mode (not always available)) sizes of the buckets 


You may present the metrics in any format you wish, but the format you choose should facilitate comparisons. 
 
Display the metrics each time you resize the table (once before the resize operation and once immediately after it’s been resized) and once the table has been fully populated.  The HashTable class will display the metrics upon resizing; the WordCount class will display the metrics once it has finished populating the table; remember that WordCount must use a method provided by HashTable to do this.  You must include a line indicating what the metrics represent (e.g. prior to resizing, immediately after resizing, fully loaded). 
 
 
Application output 
You may display the words you read in as a debugging aid.  Do not display them individually in your submitted solution. 
 
Once you have loaded all of the words into the dictionary/hash table, you should then display each word along with its frequency/number of occurrences.  For some of the files this will produce a huge amount of output.  Some of the strategies for handling this, you make group words by their frequency (for example, display the count followed by all of the words, separated by commas, multiple words to a line, which appear that number of times).  Other options might include listing only the n most and least frequently occurring words.  You could also create an .out file corresponding to each .txt file you process. 
 
The display of the metrics is separate from the display of the words and their corresponding frequencies.  It may be simplest to display the metrics before the words/frequencies.  You could also direct the metrics into a separate file (.metrics) with a name that corresponds with each .txt file. 
 
 
Discussion regarding the metrics 
Include a basic discussion of the behaviors you see in your write-up.  Given the behaviors you saw based on the metrics you collected, what conclusions can you draw about tuning a hash table for different data sets?  Include this in your presentation too! 

